Most data from APIs comes in JSON or XML format.
API 的大部分数据都是 JSON 或 XML 格式
On the left is the JSON tutorial from W3Schools and on the right is there's for XML.
左边是 W3Schools 提供的 JSON 教程 右边是 XML 教程
JSON stands for Javascript Object Notation and XML stands for Extensible Markup Language.
JSON (Javascript Object Notation) 顾名思义 JavaScript 对象标记 而 XML 代表可延伸标记语言
They both have their use cases,
这两种格式都有各自的用例
but in this lesson you'll focus on JSON.
但在本节课中 我们重点讲 JSON
In many situations, we're limited in what we can represent in tabular data.
很多情况下 能用列表数据体现的内容有限
Sometimes we have data with fields that have multiple entries like,
有时 数据字段具有多个条目
produced by, here, Kathleen Kennedy and Steven Spielberg, two entries.
比如 Produce by 中就有 Kathleen Kennedy 和 Steven Spielberg 这两个数据
And sometimes fields have subfields like release date,
有时 字段具有子字段 比如 Release date
having a date and also a location of release.
包含一个日期和发布地点
May 26 1992 in Cannes for example,
例如 1992 年 5 月 26 日 (戛纳)
then also June 11 1982 in the States.
再者 1982 年 6 月 11 日 (美国)
Release date actually has multiple entries and multiple fields.
Release date 实际上具有多个条目和字段
Representing this data in tabular form would be weird.
用列表显示此数据将会很奇怪
We'd need something like this.
我们需要这个东西
It's quite unnatural.
它很不自然
Pause the video and take in for a second how weird this feels.
暂停视频看看这有多奇怪
As displayed here, JSON is especially
正如此处所示
great for representing and accessing complicated data hierarchies,
JSON 对于展现和读取具有复杂结构的数据特别有用
like this Wikipedia info box.
比如维基百科信息框
Let's go over the structure.
我们来看看这个结构
So JSON is built on two key structures.
所以 JSON 建立在两个关键结构之上
The first one JSON objects,
第一个是 JSON 对象
which are a collection of key value pairs.
它是一批键值对
Objects are surrounded by curly braces.
对象放在花括号内
So this whole chunk of code here is one object,
所以 这一整块代码是一个对象
as displayed on the right.
如右侧所示
The left side of the screen is what the JSON code looks like.
屏幕左侧显示的是 JSON 代码
And the right side is a helpful collapsable interpretation of this code,
右侧是对本代码的可折叠解释
we can collapse as object here.
我们可以折叠此处的对象
So back to the key value pairs part of the JSON object.
回到 JSON 对象的键值对
Directed by, would be one key and Steven Spielberg would be the value for that key.
Directed by 是一个键 Steven Spielberg 是该键的值
Then after Spielberg we have a comma separating the key value pairs.
在 Spielberg 后有一个逗号隔开键值对
In Python, JSON objects are interpreted as
在 Python 语言中 JSON 对象被解释为用户可以访问的字典
dictionaries and you can access them like you would a standard Python Dict.
就像标准的 Python 字典
The second key of structure is called a JSON array,
结构的第二个键被称为 JSON 数组
which is an ordered list of values.
即含有值的有序列表
Here's an array in the value for the, produced by, key.
这是制片人 (Produced by) 键的数组
Square brackets denote an array,
方括号表示一个数组
which makes sense because in Python,
可以说得通 因为在 Python 语言下
JSON arrays are interpreted like lists and again they can be accessed as such.
JSON 数组被解释为列表 它们可以以列表形式访问
If you're familiar with other programming languages,
如果你熟悉其他它编程语言
the analogous data structure to a JSON object might be an object record struct,
JSON 对象的模拟数据结构体可能是对象记录结构体
hash table, key list or associative array.
哈希表、键列表或相联数组
Then for a JSONarray,
对于 JSON 数组
the analogous data structure might be an array,
模拟数据结构体可能是一个数组
vector or a sequence.
矢量或序列
While JSON object keys must be strings,
然而 JSON 对象键必须是字符串
you'll notice that every key on the left side here is a string.
你会注意到左侧的每个键都是一个字符串
The values for both JSON objects and arrays can be any valid JSON data type.
JSON 对象和数组的值可以是任何有效的 JSON 数据类型
So a string, number,
所以一个字符串、数字
object, array, Boolean or null.
对象、数组、布尔值或空值
There's a string, Steven Spielberg again and there's a number.
这有一个字符串 还是 “Steven Spielberg” 还有一个数字
The box office pay day in dollars or running time in minutes.
按美元计算的票房 (Box office) 或是按分钟计算的片长(Running time)
And here's the JSON array as the value for the starring key.
这里就是 JSON 数组 作为主演 (Starring) 键
Take a look at the release key here.
我们来看看这里的发布 (Release) 键
We have the string released as a key,
我们将字符串 “Release” 作为一个键
then a JSONarray, which contains two JSON objects.
然后把包含两个 JSON 对象的 JSON 数组也作为键
When objects and arrays are combined like this,
当对象和数组像这样合并后
this is called nesting.
就称为嵌套